<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Langenbecks Arch Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Langenbecks Arch Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">365</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">springeropen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Langenbeck's Archives of Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1435-2443</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1435-2451</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Springer</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12799651</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12799651.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12799651</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12799651</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41369695</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00423-025-03951-x</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3951</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Long-term clinical control in acromegaly patients with postoperative discordant nadir growth hormone during oral glucose tolerance test and insulin-like growth factor 1 levels: a retrospective observational study and literature review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names initials="T">Tomohisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaguchi</surname><given-names initials="T">Tomohiro</given-names></name><address><email>tkawaguchi0421.nsg@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yoshikazu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Endo</surname><given-names initials="H">Hidenori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03fgbah51</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.415430.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1764 884X</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurosurgery, </institution><institution>Kohnan Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>4- 20-1 Nagamachi Minami, Taihaku-ku, Sendai, 982-0012 Miyagi Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01dq60k83</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.69566.3a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2248 6943</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurosurgery, </institution><institution>Tohoku University Graduate School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Sendai, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0453fgm48</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.470214.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1771 6646</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurosurgery, </institution><institution>Senseki Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Higashimatsushima, Miyagi Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>411</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">505120</issue-id><elocation-id>46</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-15 00:25:14.200"><day>15</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="423_2025_Article_3951.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Postoperative evaluation in patients with acromegaly typically involves measuring insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1) levels and assessing growth hormone (GH) suppression via an oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT). However, discrepancies between these results are not uncommon. Despite this, there are very few studies examining long-term clinical outcomes in patients with persistent discordance between GH nadir and IGF-1 levels. In this study, we focused on such patients and conducted a retrospective analysis to clarify their mid- to long-term outcomes, alongside a review of relevant literature.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">We retrospectively reviewed patients with acromegaly who underwent transsphenoidal resection of pituitary tumors at a single institution and had serial endocrinological evaluations for more than one year between May 2005 and July 2020. Patients were divided into two groups: those with normal GH suppression during OGTT but elevated IGF-1 levels (Group I) and those with abnormal GH suppression but normal IGF-1 levels (Group II) at their 1-year postoperative evaluation. We investigated whether IGF-1 levels normalized or re-elevated over time, alongside monitoring clinical signs and comorbidity management.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">During the study period, 52 patients who were evaluated by serial IGF-1 and OGTT, 10 demonstrated discordance between GH nadir and IGF-1 levels—3 in Group I and 7 in Group II. In all Group I patients, delayed normalization of IGF-1 was observed, taking 3 to 5 years. No IGF-1 re-elevations occurred, and clinical signs and comorbidities were well controlled. In Group II, abnormal GH suppression during OGTT persisted in all patients; however, IGF-1 levels remained within the normal range without re-elevations. Clinical signs and comorbidities remained clinically stable without the need for additional therapy during the 11-year follow-up period.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Most patients achieved a mid- to long-term disease-controlled state without additional treatment. Given the potential risk of GH deficiency from further treatment, it may be reasonable to consider patients clinically controlled as long as IGF-1 levels remain normalized, with careful long-term monitoring recommended.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Acromegaly</kwd><kwd>Discordant</kwd><kwd>OGTT</kwd><kwd>IGF-1</kwd><kwd>Postoperative</kwd><kwd>GH</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2026</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">The primary treatment goal of acromegaly is the normalization of excessive growth hormone (GH) secretion, which is typically evaluated through insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1) levels and GH suppression via the oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Although these tests provide complementary information, discrepancies between the results are not uncommon, especially as remission criteria become more stringent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. While delayed normalization of IGF-1 levels is well recognized, few studies have investigated the long-term clinical outcomes in patients with persistent discordance between GH nadir and IGF-1 levels. The evidence needed to guide clinical decisions, whether these patients are in a clinically disease-controlled state without additional therapy or at risk of recurrence remains to be established.</p><p id="Par6">In this study, we focused on patients with postoperative discordant GH nadir and IGF-1 levels at the 1-year evaluation, conducting a retrospective analysis to clarify their mid- to long-term outcomes. Persistent abnormal GH suppression, which does not meet the criteria for biochemical remission over a prolonged period, may not necessarily be associated with worsened clinical control.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Patients and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Patients</title><p id="Par7">We retrospectively reviewed consecutive patients with acromegaly who underwent surgical resection at Kohnan Hospital between May 2005 and July 2020. Acromegaly was diagnosed based on biochemical findings, including elevated serum age- and sex- matched IGF-1 levels relative to the normal range and a GH nadir &gt; 0.4 mg/L during the OGTT, supported by clinical features and the presence of a pituitary tumor on magnetic resonance (MR) imaging. Definitive diagnoses were confirmed by pathological evaluation of surgical specimens. For this study, we included patients who met the following criteria: (1) Patients with IGF-1 levels and OGTT measurements performed at least twice, with the first evaluation at 1 year after surgery and the second at least 1 year later; (2) Patients with normal GH suppression but elevated IGF-1 levels, or abnormal GH suppression but normal IGF-1 levels at the 1-year evaluation. Patients who underwent reoperation or received preoperative treatments such as somatostatin analogs, dopamine agonists, or gamma knife radiosurgery were excluded from the study. All patients underwent transsphenoidal tumor resection under general anesthesia. This study was approved by the institutional review board of Kohnan Hospital. Because this was a retrospective study, the duration of follow-up varied among patients depending on the timing of their individual surgeries during the study period. Importantly, the groups were not defined by surgical era (e.g., before or after a specific year); rather, the difference in follow-up length simply reflects the natural variation in surgical dates.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Data collection and measurement</title><p id="Par8">Biochemical examinations, including OGTT and IGF-1 levels, were performed in all patients before surgery, at 1 year post-surgery, and at least annually thereafter. For the OGTT, after an overnight fast, blood samples were taken at baseline (fasting) and then at 60, 90, and 120 min after ingestion of 75 g of dextrose. GH was measured using an electro chemiluminescent immunoassay (ECLIA) with a human GH kit (Roche Diagnostic Corporation), in which standardized recombinant GH was employed. IGF-1 was also measured using an IGF-1 kit (Roche Diagnostic Corporation). The reference range for IGF-1 in the normal Japanese population was derived from a previous report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Biochemical remission was defined as the normalization of age- and sex-matched serum IGF-1 levels and GH suppression (GH nadir) to less than 0.4 mg/L during OGTT, according to current consensus guideline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">The following variables were recorded in a database: age, sex, tumor size, and Knosp grading. We also investigated clinical signs (arthralgia, hyperhidrosis, paresthesia, and headache), cancer development, cardio- or cerebrovascular events, and control of comorbidities such as hypertension and diabetes mellitus.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Evaluation</title><p id="Par10">Patients with discordant GH nadir and IGF-1 levels at 1 year post-surgery were divided into two groups for analysis: Group I (normal GH suppression with elevated IGF-1 levels) and Group II (abnormal GH suppression with normal IGF-1 levels). The difference in follow-up periods between the two groups was not intentional; it arose because surgeries were performed at different time points, resulting in variable follow-up durations at the time of analysis. Ten patients with discordant GH nadir and IGF-1 levels at 1 year post-surgery were divided into two groups for analysis: Group I (normal GH suppression with elevated IGF-1 levels) and Group II (abnormal GH suppression with normal IGF-1 levels). During the follow-up period, we assessed whether IGF-1 levels were maintained within the normal range or re-elevated, alongside monitoring clinical signs and comorbidities. The occurrence of mortality, cancer development, and cardio- or cerebrovascular events was also investigated.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Study participants</title><p id="Par11">A flowchart illustrating the patient inclusion and exclusion process is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. 52 patients had sufficient endocrinological data in the study. 10 met the remission criteria at 1 year after surgery. On the other hand, 32 patients did not meet the remission criteria with elevated IGF-1 levels and abnormal GH suppression and required additional treatments, such as medical therapy. The 10 patients who showed discordant GH nadir and IGF-1 levels at the 1-year postoperative evaluation and received subsequent serial evaluations were finally included and analyzed in this study. There are many excluded patients because most of these achieved biochemical remission early in the postoperative period and were subsequently evaluated primarily by IGF-1, with normal IGF-1 levels maintained.</p><p id="Par12">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Flow chart of the current study population</p><p> IGF-1, insulin-like growth factor-1; OGTT, oral glucose tolerance test</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e275" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="423_2025_3951_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Basic characteristics</title><p id="Par13">In this study, the 10 patients eligible for analysis were followed for a median of 5 years (range: 2–11 years). The basic characteristics of the enrolled patients, including age, proportion of smaller tumors (&lt; 10 mm), Knosp grade, pathology, and tumor recurrence, are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><p id="Par14">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristic of enrolled patients IGF-1: insulin-like growth factor-1, PitNET pituitary neuroendocrine tumor</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients with Discordant (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, range (median)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44–75 (56)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (50%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maximum tumor size with &lt; 10 mm</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (30%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Knosp Grade</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gross total removal</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9(90%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pathology</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Somatotroph PitNET</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Somatotroph plurihormonal PitNET</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Follow up period, range (median, years)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2–11(4.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recurrence or regrowth of tumor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Re-elevation of IGF-1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par15">Of the 10 patients, 3 had tumors smaller than 10 mm, while the others had tumors ranging from 10 to 23 mm in diameter. Post operative MR imaging revealed that gross total removal was achieved in all patients except one, and all were observed without additional therapy. At the 1-year postoperative evaluation, 3 patients showed normal GH suppression with elevated IGF-1 levels (Group I), while the remaining 7 showed abnormal GH suppression with normal IGF-1 levels (Group II).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Group I patients: normal GH suppression with elevated IGF-1 levels</title><p id="Par16">Group I included patients Case 1–3 (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Preoperative IGF-1 concentrations ranged from 457 to 1,523 ng/mL (1.03–1.27 x upper limit of normal (ULN)), and GH levels ranged from 2.05 to 44.9 ng/mL, with no suppression during OGTT. Post operative MR imaging showed that gross total removal was achieved in 2 cases. In all cases, IGF-1 levels continued to decrease after the 1-year evaluation, eventually falling below the upper limit of the reference range. The time to IGF-1 normalization ranged from 3 to 5 years. During the follow-up period (5–7 years), IGF-1 levels remained within the reference range throughout the follow-up period, with no evidence of re-elevations, even in the case of subtotal removal. Postoperatively, GH nadir levels remained below 0.4 ng/mL in all patients, with no evidence of re-elevation during the follow-up period. No tumor recurrence or regrowth was observed. Clinical signs improved postoperatively and did not recur, with good control of comorbidities. There were no mortalities, cancer, renal failure, hepatic disease or cardio- or cerebrovascular events. In addition, in most patients, antihypertensive and antidiabetic medications could be discontinued or reduced during follow-up, indicating improvement in metabolic sequelae after surgical cure.</p><p id="Par17">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Characteristics of postoperative patients with discordant between IGF-1 and GH nadir after OGTT</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">No</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Group</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Age</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sex</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Tumor size(mm)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Knosp<break/>grade</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Tumor removal</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Commodities</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Preoperative</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1 year</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">last F/U</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">F/U years</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Control of<break/>commodities</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IGF-1</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GH nadir</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IGF-1</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GH nadir</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IGF-1</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GH nadir</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 × 16 × 14</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Subtotal</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HT, DM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>457</bold>
</p><p>(54–167)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">not suppressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>212</bold>
</p><p>(53–165)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.32</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>113</p><p>(46–154)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.95</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 × 15 × 19</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GTR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HT, DM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>1523</bold>
</p><p>(85–240)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">not suppressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>244</bold>
</p><p>(84–239)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>155</p><p>(81–235)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 × 20 × 19</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GTR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HT, DM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>573</bold>
</p><p>(52–163)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">not suppressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>168</bold>
</p><p>(50–160)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>148</p><p>(45–152)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.28</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 × 9 × 9</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GTR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>377</bold>
</p><p>(71–203)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>200</p><p>(70–201)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.91</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>155</p><p>(68–196)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1.12</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 × 7 × 7</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GTR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HT</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>460</bold>
</p><p>(75–210)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>155</p><p>(74–208)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.86</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>123</p><p>(72–205)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.52</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">not changed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 × 10 × 9</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GTR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HT</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>605</bold>
</p><p>(81–235</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>154</p><p>(80–233)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.56</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>116</p><p>(79–232)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.43</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 × 11 × 10</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GTR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HT</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>409</bold>
</p><p>(85–240)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>128</p><p>(84–239)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1.77</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>112</p><p>(82–236)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1.74</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 × 17 × 18</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GTR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HT</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>435</bold>
</p><p>(88–229)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>158</p><p>(87–226)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1.20</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>90</p><p>(81–218)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>2.43</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 × 17 × 16</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GTR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>1017</bold>
</p><p>(85–240)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>199</p><p>(84–239)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1.19</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>195</p><p>(84–238)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1.22</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 × 4 × 7</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GTR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HT, DM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<bold>304</bold>
</p><p>(88–246)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>243</p><p>(87–245)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.98</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>210</p><p>(79–232)</p></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1.45</bold>
</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">good</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">DM</italic> diabetes mellitus, <italic toggle="yes">F</italic> female, <italic toggle="yes">F/U</italic> follow up, <italic toggle="yes">GH</italic> growth hormone, <italic toggle="yes">GTR</italic> gross total removal, <italic toggle="yes">HT</italic> hypertension, <italic toggle="yes">IGF-1</italic> insulin-like growth factor-1, <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> male, The value of IGF-1 (ng/ml) and GH nadir (ng/ml) demonstrated, and abnormal vale was marked in bold. IGF-1 was demonstrated with ± 2 standard deviation(SD)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Group II patients: abnormal GH suppression with normal IGF-1 levels</title><p id="Par18">Group II included patients Case 4–10 (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Preoperative IGF-1 concentrations ranged from 304 to 1,017 ng/mL, and nadir GH levels during OGTT ranged from 2.02 to 27.34 ng/mL. Body mass index (BMI) was ranged 19.3–27.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. There were no patients with low body weight (BMI under 18.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>). Gross total removal was achieved in all cases, and no intraoperative cavernous sinus invasion was observed. During the follow-up period (2–11 years), although GH nadir levels remained above 0.4 mg/L in all patients, IGF-1 levels were maintained within the normal range throughout the follow-up period, with no evidence of re-elevations. Clinical symptoms improved early postoperatively and did not recur and no residual tumor or recurrence was visible on MR imaging. Comorbid conditions, such as diabetes mellitus and hypertension, were well controlled, with no clinical deterioration or requirement for additional treatment during follow-up.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Illustrative case</title><p id="Par19">A 44-year-old woman (Case No. 8 in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) was referred to our hospital with chronic headaches and bitemporal hemianopsia. She had a history of hypertension, sleep apnea, and carpal tunnel syndrome. Elevated serum IGF-1 levels and abnormal GH suppression during OGTT were observed (IGF-1: 435 (normal range: 88–229) ng/mL; basal GH: 32.6 ng/mL; nadir GH: 27.3 ng/mL). Postcontrast T1-weighted MR imaging revealed a suprasellar round mass (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). Transsphenoidal resection of the pituitary tumor was performed, resulting in gross total removal (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). Immunohistochemical analysis revealed a plurihormonal adenoma. The postoperative course was uneventful, with improvements in her chronic headaches and visual disturbances. At the 1-year postoperative evaluation, IGF-1 levels had normalized; however, GH levels remained unsuppressed, staying above 0.4 mg/L during OGTT. Over 6 years of follow-up, abnormal GH suppression persisted, while IGF-1 levels continued to decrease (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>D). No tumor recurrence was observed on MR imaging (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C).</p><p id="Par20">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Illustrated case (Case No 8 in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). <bold>A</bold>: Postcontrast T1-weighted magnetic resonance (MR) imaging showed an enhanced suprasellar round mass, compressing optic chiasm. <bold>B</bold>: Postoperative MR imaging reveals no tumor remnant. <bold>C</bold>: At the 6-year evaluation post-surgery, no tumor recurrence was observed. <bold>D</bold>: Summary of biochemical tests, including serum IGF-1 levels, basal serum GH levels, and GH nadir during OGTT. GH, Growth hormone; IGF-1, insulin-like growth factor-1; OGTT, oral glucose tolerance test</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1002" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="423_2025_3951_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par21">This study investigated the mid- to long-term biochemical and clinical outcomes in acromegaly patients with postoperative discordant GH nadir and IGF-1 levels. Our results show that IGF-1 levels in all patients normalized and remained within the normal range without additional treatment, while GH levels also remained suppressed during follow-up. Clinical symptoms and comorbidities were well controlled. In the literature, several authors have reported observational studies that include postoperative discordance, summarized in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. There are two patterns of discordant GH nadir and IGF-1 biochemical status. The first pattern involves normal GH suppression with elevated IGF-1 levels, as seen in Group (I) Delayed normalization of IGF-1 levels is expected under normal GH suppression (i.e., less than 0.4 mg/L), sometimes taking 12 months or more after surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Among our 3 cases in Group I, delayed normalization of IGF-1 was observed, even in a case with tumor remnants. In our case, immunohistochemistry revealed a plurihormonal adenoma. Although some studies have suggested that certain histological subtypes, including plurihormonal or sparsely-granulated adenomas, may show delayed biochemical remission, the evidence remains inconclusive. Delayed IGF-1 normalization is likely multifactorial, involving residual tumor activity, GH secretion dynamics, and metabolic factors. In addition, the residual lesion remained unchanged on MR imaging for 7 years and appeared to be endocrinologically and biologically inactive, as no hormonal re-elevation was observed during follow-up. This may suggest partial impairment of the tumor’s vascular supply during surgery, leading to loss of secretory activity rather than size reduction. The second biochemical pattern involves abnormal GH suppression with normal IGF-1 levels, as seen in Group (II) In our series, this pattern was observed in 7 of 52 patients (13.5%), which is generally consistent with previous reports describing an incidence of 5–35.5% among postoperative patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. In a literature review, including our seven cases, a total of 89 patients were categorized into this pattern, with approximately 80% maintaining normal IGF-1 levels. Intraoperative findings of no cavernous sinus invasion and gross total removal have been suggested to correlate with a lower rate of IGF-1 re-elevation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. All 7 of our cases achieved gross total removal, and no cavernous sinus invasion was observed intraoperatively. Although discordant biochemical status persisted, IGF-1 levels remained within the normal range for up to 11 years. However, in our review, 15 out of 81 patients showed IGF-1 re-elevation. This indicates that the outcome of this biochemical pattern remains undefined and uncertain, even after many years, due to the potential risk of IGF-1 re-elevation. Nevertheless, in patients without risk factors such as incomplete resection or cavernous sinus invasion, long-term IGF-1 normalization is likely to be expected.</p><p id="Par22">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Summary of observational study describing postoperative discordance between IGF-1 and OGTT</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study design</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Details of Discordance</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of<break/> patients</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F/U period<break/>(years)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Evaluation of IGF-1 <break/>at last F/U</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">clinical symptom</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ronchi et al. (2007)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">normal IGF-1 with GHn &gt; 0.26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 patients</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All patients: normal range</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Brzana et al. (2012)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mild elevated IGF-1 with GHn &lt; 0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 patients</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 patients: normal range</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nishioka et al. (2017)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">normal IGF-1 with GHn &gt; 0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 patients</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4–6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 patients: re-elevation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Graillon et al. (2020)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">normal IGF-1 with GHn &gt; 0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 patients</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5–11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 patients: normal range</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 patients: re-elevation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Freda et al. (2021)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">normal IGF-1 with GHn &gt; 0.14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 patients</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9–22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 patients: normal range</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 patients: re-elevation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">not consistent</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Present study</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">elevated IGF-1 with GHn &lt; 0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 patients</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5–7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All patients: normal range</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">normal IGF-1 with GHn &gt; 0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 patients</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2–11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All patients: normal range</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">F/U</italic> follow up, <italic toggle="yes">GH</italic> growth hormone, <italic toggle="yes">GHn</italic> GH nadir, <italic toggle="yes">IGF-1</italic> insulin-like growth factor-1, <italic toggle="yes">N/A</italic> not available, <italic toggle="yes">OGTT</italic> oral glucose tolerance test</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par23">The exact reasons for discordant GH nadir and IGF-1 levels are unknown. Certain conditions, including chronic renal failure, chronic hepatitis, hyperthyroidism, type 1 diabetes mellitus, oral estrogen use, alcohol abuse, anorexia nervosa, and GH receptor polymorphism, may induce abnormal GH suppression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. It is also suggested that dysregulation of GH secretion persists despite successful treatment of acromegaly, potentially due to disruption of its neural or anatomical systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Abnormal GH suppression has been shown to cause mild GH excess, as seen through greater mean GH levels during hourly sampling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. IGF-1 levels may remain normal if GH secretion is only mildly elevated. In this context, regardless of the cause, it is reasonable to consider the possibility of mild GH excess in patients with discordant results.</p><p id="Par24">The most important concern is the clinical outcome resulting from postoperative abnormal GH suppression and mild GH excess. GH suppression during OGTT plays a less clear role in clinical outcomes compared to IGF-1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. In our observational study, disease-associated symptoms and comorbidities (hypertension, diabetes mellitus, heart failure and headache) did not worsen in patients with abnormal GH suppression but normal IGF-1 levels. Previous literature also lacks consistent patterns of worsening signs and symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Although mild GH excess presents a potential risk for IGF-1 re-elevation, there is insufficient evidence to suggest that GH levels need to be suppressed to within the normal range with additional treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Further treatment to lower GH levels may increase the risk of GH deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Stricter biochemical control does not always result in more effective clinical control. Given the limited sample size, our findings should be interpreted with caution. However, as long as IGF-1 normalization is maintained, these patients may be considered clinically controlled. In such cases, careful observation with monitoring of IGF-1 and GH levels could be considered reasonable, and additional treatment may not be immediately necessary.</p><p id="Par25">Our study has several limitations. First, number of patients is limited. Larger studies are needed to confirm our results. Second, histological diagnosis is heterogenous. In this study, there were 4 patients with somatotroph plurihormonal PitNET, which all were GH/PRL co-producing tumor (PRL levels rage:17.2-114.5 ng/mL). Among them, two were in Group1, the others were in GroupⅡ. Unfortunately, only four cases were available, and no distinctive correlation was observed between histological types and clinical characteristics. Third, the mechanisms underlying why patients may remain asymptomatic despite not meeting postoperative remission criteria is not clear. One possible explanation is the balance between hormone secretion levels and tissue sensitivity.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par26">In our observation of postoperative acromegaly patients with discordance between GH nadir by OGTT and IGF-1 levels, a mid- to long-term clinically disease-controlled state was achievable without additional treatment. As long as IGF-1 normalization is maintained without clinical symptoms, it may be reasonable to consider these patients as clinically controlled, with meticulous observation recommended rather than additional treatment.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>None.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>T.I. and T.K. wrote the main manuscript text, and Y.O. and H.E. made substantial contributions to the study design and data collection. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No extramural funding was used in support of this work.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par27">This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Kohnan Hospital, Sendai, Miyagi, Japan (IRB approval number: 2023-0118-03). Written informed consent to participate in this study was obtained from all participants.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par28">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleseriu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biller</surname><given-names>BMK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freda</surname><given-names>PU</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A pituitary society update to acromegaly management guidelines</article-title><source>Pituitary</source><year>2021</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11102-020-01091-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33079318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7864830</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Fleseriu M, Biller BMK, Freda PU et al (2021) A pituitary society update to acromegaly management guidelines. Pituitary 24:1–13. 10.1007/s11102-020-01091-7<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33079318</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11102-020-01091-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7864830</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melmed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronstein</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chanson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A consensus statement on acromegaly therapeutic outcomes</article-title><source>Nat Rev Endocrinol</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>552</fpage><lpage>561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41574-018-0058-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30050156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7136157</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Melmed S, Bronstein MD, Chanson P et al (2018) A consensus statement on acromegaly therapeutic outcomes. Nat Rev Endocrinol 14:552–561. 10.1038/s41574-018-0058-5<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30050156</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41574-018-0058-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7136157</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freda</surname><given-names>PU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monitoring of acromegaly: what should be performed when GH and IGF-1 levels are discrepant?</article-title><source>Clin Endocrinol (Oxf)</source><year>2009</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2265.2009.03556.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19226264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3654652</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Freda PU (2009) Monitoring of acromegaly: what should be performed when GH and IGF-1 levels are discrepant? Clin Endocrinol (Oxf) 71:166–170. 10.1111/j.1365-2265.2009.03556.x<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19226264</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2265.2009.03556.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3654652</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graillon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castinetti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boucekine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fluctuation analysis of postoperative secretory status in patients operated for acromegaly</article-title><source>Ann Endocrinol (Paris)</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ando.2019.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31982107</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Graillon T, Castinetti F, Boucekine M et al (2020) Fluctuation analysis of postoperative secretory status in patients operated for acromegaly. Ann Endocrinol (Paris) 8:11–17. 10.1016/j.ando.2019.11.002<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ando.2019.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31982107</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isojima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimatsu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Standardized centile curves and reference intervals of serum insulin-like growth factor-I (IGF-I) levels in a normal Japanese population using the LMS method</article-title><source>Endocr J</source><year>2012</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1507/endocrj.ej12-0110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22673406</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Isojima T, Shimatsu A, Yokoya S et al (2012) Standardized centile curves and reference intervals of serum insulin-like growth factor-I (IGF-I) levels in a normal Japanese population using the LMS method. Endocr J 59:771–780. 10.1507/endocrj.ej12-0110<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22673406</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1507/endocrj.ej12-0110</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronchi</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arosio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizzo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lania</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beck-Peccoz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adequacy of current postglucose GH nadir limit (&lt; 1 microg/l) to define long-lasting remission of acromegalic disease</article-title><source>Clin Endocrinol (Oxf)</source><year>2007</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>538</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2265.2007.02769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17371472</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Ronchi CL, Arosio M, Rizzo E, Lania AG, Beck-Peccoz P, Spada A (2007) Adequacy of current postglucose GH nadir limit (&lt; 1 microg/l) to define long-lasting remission of acromegalic disease. Clin Endocrinol (Oxf) 4:538–432. 10.1111/j.1365-2265.2007.02769<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2265.2007.02769.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17371472</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brzana</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yedinak</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delashaw</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gultelkin</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleseriu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discordant growth hormone and IGF-1 levels post pituitary surgery in patients with acromegaly Naive to medical therapy and radiation: what to follow, GH or IGF-1 values?</article-title><source>Pituitary</source><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11102-011-0369-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22183781</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Brzana JA, Yedinak CG, Delashaw JB, Gultelkin HS, Cook D, Fleseriu M (2012) Discordant growth hormone and IGF-1 levels post pituitary surgery in patients with acromegaly Naive to medical therapy and radiation: what to follow, GH or IGF-1 values? Pituitary. 10.1007/s11102-011-0369-1. 15:562 – 70<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22183781</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11102-011-0369-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuhara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Okada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takeshita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pitfalls in early biochemical evaluation after transsphenoidal surgery in patients with acromegaly</article-title><source>Endocr J</source><year>2017</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1073</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1507/endocrj.EJ17-0261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28835593</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Nishioka H, Fukuhara N, Yamaguchi-Okada M, Takeshita A, Takeuchi Y, Yamada S (2017) Pitfalls in early biochemical evaluation after transsphenoidal surgery in patients with acromegaly. Endocr J 64:1073–1078. 10.1507/endocrj.EJ17-0261<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28835593</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1507/endocrj.EJ17-0261</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freda</surname><given-names>PU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes-Vidal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognostic value of nadir GH levels for long-term biochemical remission or recurrence in surgically treated acromegaly</article-title><source>Pituitary</source><year>2021</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11102-020-01094-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33124000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7969360</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Freda PU, Bruce JN, Reyes-Vidal C et al (2021) Prognostic value of nadir GH levels for long-term biochemical remission or recurrence in surgically treated acromegaly. Pituitary 24:170–183. 10.1007/s11102-020-01094-4<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33124000</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11102-020-01094-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7969360</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tokimura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanaya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gradual declination of IGF-1 over a year after transsphenoidal adenomectomy of GH producing pituitary adenomas</article-title><source>Endocr J</source><year>2011</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1087</fpage><lpage>1091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1507/endocrj.ej11-0146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22033477</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Fujio S, Tokimura H, Hanaya R et al (2011) Gradual declination of IGF-1 over a year after transsphenoidal adenomectomy of GH producing pituitary adenomas. Endocr J 58:1087–1091. 10.1507/endocrj.ej11-0146<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22033477</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1507/endocrj.ej11-0146</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term changes in serum IGF-1 levels after successful surgical treatment of growth hormone-secreting pituitary adenoma</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source><year>2013</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1227/01.neu.0000431480.87160.84</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23728452</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Shin MS, Yu JH, Choi JH et al (2013) Long-term changes in serum IGF-1 levels after successful surgical treatment of growth hormone-secreting pituitary adenoma. Neurosurgery 73:473–479. 10.1227/01.neu.0000431480.87160.84<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23728452</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1227/01.neu.0000431480.87160.84</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akirov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masri-Iraqi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dotan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biochemical diagnosis of acromegaly</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1147</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10051147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33803429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7967116</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Akirov A, Masri-Iraqi H, Dotan I, Shimon I (2021) The biochemical diagnosis of acromegaly. J Clin Med 10:1147. 10.3390/jcm10051147<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33803429</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jcm10051147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7967116</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giustina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cimino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angelini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pontecorvi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marinis</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of growth hormone receptor d3 and full-length isoforms on biochemical treatment outcomes in acromegaly</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2009</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>2015</fpage><lpage>2022</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2008-1337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19336510</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Bianchi A, Giustina A, Cimino V, Pola R, Angelini F, Pontecorvi A, Marinis LD (2009) Influence of growth hormone receptor d3 and full-length isoforms on biochemical treatment outcomes in acromegaly. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 94:2015–2022. 10.1210/jc.2008-1337<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19336510</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/jc.2008-1337</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamenický</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chanson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth hormone response to oral glucose load: from normal to pathological conditions</article-title><source>Neuroendocrinology</source><year>2019</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000497214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30685760</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Hage M, Kamenický P, Chanson P (2019) Growth hormone response to oral glucose load: from normal to pathological conditions. Neuroendocrinology 108:244–255. 10.1159/000497214<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30685760</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000497214</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friberg</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barkan</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistence of rapid growth hormone (GH) pulsatility after successful removal of GH-producing pituitary tumors</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1994</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1403</fpage><lpage>1410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jcem.78.6.7911124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7911124</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Ho PJ, Jaffe CA, Friberg RD, Chandler WH, Barkan AL (1994) Persistence of rapid growth hormone (GH) pulsatility after successful removal of GH-producing pituitary tumors. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 78:1403–1410. 10.1210/jcem.78.6.7911124<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7911124</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/jcem.78.6.7911124</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graillon</surname><given-names>PU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuruzzaman</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundeen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Significance of abnormal nadir growth hormone levels after oral glucose in postoperative patients with acromegaly in remission with normal insulin-like growth factor-I levels</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2004</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2003-031316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14764751</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Graillon PU, Nuruzzaman AT, Reyes CM, Sundeen R, Post KD (2004) Significance of abnormal nadir growth hormone levels after oral glucose in postoperative patients with acromegaly in remission with normal insulin-like growth factor-I levels. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 89:495–500. 10.1210/jc.2003-031316<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14764751</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/jc.2003-031316</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexopoulou</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bex</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>T’sjoen, Welkeniers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maiter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Divergence between growth hormone and insulin-like growth factor-i concentrations in the follow-up of acromegaly</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2008</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1324</fpage><lpage>1330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2007-2104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18230660</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Alexopoulou O, Bex M, Abs R, T’sjoen, Welkeniers B, Maiter D (2008) Divergence between growth hormone and insulin-like growth factor-i concentrations in the follow-up of acromegaly. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 93:1324–1330. 10.1210/jc.2007-2104<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18230660</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/jc.2007-2104</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jönsson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trainer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shalet</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><collab>KIMS International Board</collab></person-group><article-title>Seeking the optimal target range for insulin-like growth factor I during the treatment of adult growth hormone disorders</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2003</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>5865</fpage><lpage>5870</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2002-021741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14671182</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Mukherjee A, Monson JP, Jönsson PJ, Trainer PJ, Shalet SM, KIMS International Board (2003) Seeking the optimal target range for insulin-like growth factor I during the treatment of adult growth hormone disorders. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 88:5865–5870. 10.1210/jc.2002-021741<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14671182</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/jc.2002-021741</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuhara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GH deficiency in patients after cure of acromegaly by surgery alone</article-title><source>Eur J Endocrinol</source><year>2011</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>873</fpage><lpage>879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1530/EJE-11-0657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21964960</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Yamada S, Fukuhara N, Nishioka H et al (2011) GH deficiency in patients after cure of acromegaly by surgery alone. Eur J Endocrinol 165:873–879. 10.1530/EJE-11-0657<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21964960</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1530/EJE-11-0657</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>